טוב, tov, today's דף daf in the בבלי Bavli is ו. Vav.
We pick up at the bottom of ה עמוד ב, Hey amud
bet, actually not at the bottom, we're a little bit behind. We
were dealing with the whole story about where this idea of יורה
יורה yoreh yoreh comes from.
The גמרא Gemara says that rabbis needed the authority to be דן,
dan, which was the whole case about being נוטל רשות notel reshut
in order to exempt them from payment if they ruled incorrectly, from
having liability if they ruled incorrectly. And then it said, but at
least the בבלי Bavli said that that authority from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael does not work for בבל. Bavel. But then it told these
whole stories about רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya's nephews going to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, going to בבל, Bavel, and that's the classic basis of
יורה יורה, yoreh yoreh, ידין ידין. yadin yadin. Do they have a
right to judge, do they have a right to do
דיני ממונות? dinei mamonot? And that's where we get that whole thing
from. And the גמרא Gemara says, why do you need that authority
if you're going to be exempt, if the authority from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael does not help for בבל? Bavel? So then okay, it
was dealing with those like border communities and that's why it was
needed. So that set question about the authorization, the licensing to exempt
you from payment. But the interesting thing for us is יורה יורה
yoreh yoreh becomes a different issue which has nothing to do with
דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, just has to do with somebody coming and
asking you a
הלכה halachic שאלה, she'elah, איסור והיתר. issur v'heter. So what's the whole
purpose of licensing there? That's not about exempting from payment, that's not
about authority to force people to come to judgment. So that
is basically licensing because not everybody who's a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
is fit to be a rabbi and fit to פסקן, pasken, and
it told stories about a guy who just articulated his words incorrectly
and led to people to do a mistake and therefore this is
important because people should know not to hire somebody as a rabbi
unless he has received this authority from his רב. rav. And that's
right, that became the language used for giving, essentially telling communities this
person has been licensed or he can be trusted to be a
rabbi. Okay, so that was a story about רבי Rebbi coming to
a certain place and finding out that this rabbi פסק paskened incorrectly.
And there it said like this: שעה, sha'ah, באותה שעה, be-osa sha'ah,
we'll start with the line that says שעה, sha'ah, it's almost exactly
midway in ה עמוד ב. Hey amud bet. באותה שעה גזרו, be-osa
sha'ah gazru, at that time they established, תלמיד אל יורה אלא אם
כן נוטל רשות מרבו. talmid al yoreh ella im ken notal reshut
mi-rabbo. A תלמיד talmid cannot rule unless he, I said they said
community, but here it's framed in terms of the person. You do
not have a right to פסקן pasken until you've been given that
right from your רב rav to פסקן. pasken. So I said that
incorrectly. Okay, in practice in the Middle Ages and whatever and when
they all started the whole giving of סמיכה, semicha, the contemporary סמיכה,
semicha, it was really also a way of telling communities you could
be confident to hire this guy. But anyway in the גמרא Gemara
it's framed in terms of the person. You, I don't care how
big of a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham you are, if
I have to say that I feel you can be trusted to
פסקן. pasken. You know enough about people, you know enough about how
to articulate your words so that they're heard correctly. Okay, so you
do not have a right to פסקן pasken for other people until
you have been granted authority by your רבי. rebbi.
Yes, and I can't help but think of like this may be
a little bit too metaphorical, but ביצועים bitzuim is in ביצוע bitzua
and טמא... tama...
oh that's interesting. Is it if the ביצועים bitzuim is it echoing
or prefiguring the idea of ביצוע bitzua that's coming up? That could
be. Okay, so now we have another story. תנחום בריה דרבי אמי
אקלע לחצר, Tanchum brei de-Rabbi Ami ikla le-Chasor, so תנחום Tanchum the
son of רבי אמי Rabbi Ami came to this place חצר, Chasor,
דרש להו darash lehu and he explicated to them מותר ללסות חטים
בפסח. mutar lalsot chitim be-Pesach. So you're allowed to go ahead and
to do I don't know what the English word for this is,
but basically put water on the grain in order to get off
the
husk and you can do that on פסח Pesach and you're not
afraid that the process of doing that will turn the grain into
חמץ. chametz. Okay, so where were we?
אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to him, לאו רבי מני דמן
צור איכא הכא? lav Rabbi Mani de-min Tzor ika hacha? How could
you be telling us this? רבי מני Reb Mani from צור Tzor
is here. דתניא, De-tanya, these townspeople knew a lot. They were quoting
to this rabbi a ברייתא, braita, and we taught in the ברייתא,
braita, תלמיד אל יורה הלכה במקום רבו, talmid al yoreh halacha be-makom
rabbo, you can't פסקן pasken in the place where your רבי rebbi
is, אלא אם כן היה רחוק ממנו שלש פרסאות, ella im ken
haya rachok mimenu shalosh parsa'ot, you have to be three פרסאות parsas
distant from him, otherwise you are it's seen as disrespectful to your
רבי. rebbi. כנגד מחנה ישראל, keneged machaneh Yisrael, like the distance of
the whole camp of ישראל Yisrael in the desert. אמר להו, Amar
lehu, לאו אדעתי, lav ada'ati, he said oh I didn't realize, I
didn't realize that my רבי rebbi was here in this town, otherwise
I wouldn't have פסק. paskened. Okay, so here's another story which is
that you're not allowed to, not only are you not allowed to
פסקן pasken in general until you're authorized by your רבי, rebbi, but
even after you've been authorized by your רבי rebbi to פסקן, pasken,
you're not allowed to פסקן pasken if you're in his same area
and zone cause that's being disrespectful to his authority. And also what
like always today שבת shabbos yes no you
know right what right
correct also
what constitutes פסק psak
is also is also a good is also a good question. Yes,
so you know, but here, authority is needed to פסקן pasken all
together and that doesn't allow you to פסקן pasken in the רבי'ס
rebbe's presence with the presence defined as same town. Mike raised a
good question: what constitutes פסק psak פסקנינג? paskening? And also the question
is, is there a way to give authority that allows one to
פסקן pasken even in their רבי'ס rebbe's presence? Okay, and that's the
way that some people understand the importance of סמיכה semicha is to
not just allow פסקנינג paskening all together, but to allow פסקנינג paskening
in the presence of the רבי. rebbe. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
אמר
להו, Amar lehu, okay, we just said, רבי חייא חזא להו גברא,
Rabbi Chiya chaza lehu gavra, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya saw a person
דהוה קאים בבית הקברות d'havei ka'im beveit hakevarot that was standing in
the cemetery. אמר ליה, Amar lei, לאו בן איש פלוני כהן את,
lav bin ish ploni kohen at, aren't you a כהן? kohen? אמר
ליה, Amar lei, אין, in, yes, but אבוה דהוא גברא, avuhu dehu
gavra, but the father of this man, meaning my father, גבה עיניים
הוה, geva einayim hava, he had his eyes were high, meaning he,
you know, he exactly, he followed his eyes,
ונתן עיניו בגרושה, venatan einav bigrushah, and he went and he married
a divorced woman, וחיללו, v'chiluhu, and he made me a חלל. chalal.
Okay, so therefore I do not have the sanctity of a כהן.
kohen. Now that's not exactly clear what that has anything to do
with the story above. רש"י Rashi gives a different version that this
was part of the story of רבי, Rebbe, but anyway we're going
to move on. Now back to this idea of granting authority. So
the בבלי Bavli says the following: פשיטא לפלגא הכא נמי דמהני. Pshita
lepalga hachi nami demahani. It's clear that if you give somebody partial
authority, that works, because we discussed before about giving them authority
for דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, but not for מתיר בכורות. matir bechorot.
So partial authority works, licensing. Okay, that's פשיטא דמהני. pshita demahani. על
תנאי מאי? Al tnai mai? What if it's conditional? Like only for
a limited amount of time, or only under certain conditions? תא שמע,
Ta shma, come and hear. דאמר ליה D'amar lei רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan לרב שמן: l'Rav Shemen: הרי אתה ברשותנו, harei ata birshuteinu, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to רב שמן: Rav Shemen: You are under
our, you have our authority, עד שתבוא אצלנו, ad shetavo etzleinu, until
you return to us. So meaning that we are granting you this
authority.
That's on place. That's only certain places. It's unconditional authority to certain
places.
Yeah,
yeah, I mean it's true, but the ירושלמי Yerushalmi sort of sees
it in any ways, any type of limit and condition. You have
the right to פסקן, pasken, you know, when you're away. You have
the right to פסקן pasken for a certain amount of time. You
have the right whatever. It's some type of a limiting. Okay, it's
not only in certain areas, because maybe you only have knowledge in
certain areas. You know, you could say once you're giving me authority,
you're acknowledging that I have the knowledge, so why should you be
able to limit it by time and place? So it sees the
whole thing as the same. Fine. So that's the end, that's we
should have finished yesterday. That's the end of the discussions of the
granting of authority or licensing. Now we get back to this question
about the issue about judging alone, you know, as opposed to judging
with a בית דין Beit Din of three or whatever. Because you'll
remember that yesterday the גמרא Gemara said that if you're a מומחה
לרבים, mumche l'rabbim, right, that that works, to judge alone, and but
if they accepted your authority, you know, you don't need to, you
know, then you don't presumably then even if you're not a מומחה.
mumche. Okay, so let's take a look here at
where the גמרא Gemara goes. It says the following: גופא. Gufa. אמר
שמואל: Amar Shmuel: בי שדנו דיניהם דין אלא שנקרא בית דין חצוף.
bei shedanu dineihem din ella shenikra beit din chatzuf.
If two people judged, it's binding, but they are like a חצוף
chatzuf בית דין. Beit Din. יתיב Yosef רב נחמן וקאמר להלא שמעתתא.
Rav Nachman vekamar lehala shmaitas. רב נחמן Rav Nachman was telling over
this discussion. איתיבי רב לרב נחמן: Eitivei Rav l'Rav Nachman: אפילו שנים
מזכין או שנים מחייבין, afillu shnayim mezakin o shnayim mechayivin, ואחד אומר
איני יודע, v'echad omer eini yodea, יוסיפו הדיינין. yosifu hadayanin. If you
have a בית דין Beit Din of three and two say that
you're guilty and two say you're innocent and the third one says
I don't know, so that's not a good judgment. You should say,
well, who cares? Even if he found the opposite, it would be
two against one. But no, if he sort of says I don't
know, it's like he's not there and you're only left with two
and you have to add more judges. Okay.
ואי איתא, V'i issa, if it's true, להוי כשנים שדנו, lehavi kishnayim
shedanu, then if it's true that two people בדיעבד bedi'avad constitute a
בית דין, Beit Din, so even if one person like you know
says I don't know and it's like he's not there,
why can't we just go forward if two people at the end
of the day constitute a בית דין? Beit Din? So the גמרא
Gemara says: No. שאני התם דמעיקרא דעתא דתלתא יתבי. Shani hatam d'me'ikara
da'ata ditlata yasvi.
That's different. When you constitute a בית דין Beit Din of three,
then you're defining the unit as three and then you need the
whole בית דין Beit Din to come to a conclusion. And the
saying I don't know is not giving a judgment. So, which is
very interesting. So it's like if you started with three and one
of them said I'm out of here and I'm leaving, somehow and
you can't finish with two. That's worse than starting with two. Alright,
which is interesting. You could have thought the opposite. If you start
with three and you end with two, at least you know they're
representing the whole three. But anyways, that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
Yes, Mike?
In your doing the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it said, you know, when that
guy said he didn't know then you could essentially do פשרה peshara
then, right?
Yeah, we'll get to פשרה. peshara. Okay. הכא לאו אדעתא דתלתא יתבי,
Hacha lav ada'ata ditlata yasvi, but when you start, don't start with
three and you start with two, that's when we say that it
could work. Okay. איתיבי רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר. Eitivei Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer. I'll ask you, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says. הדין בשלושה פשרה בשניים, hadin b'shlosha psharah b'shnayim, that
judgment is three, but compromise is two suffices. יפה כוח פשרה מכוח
הדין, yafe koach psharah mikoach hadin, compromise is better in the
following way: ששניים שדנו בעלי דינים יכולים לחזור בהן, sheshnayim shedannu ba'alei
dinim yecholim lachzor bahen, if two are in judgment then you could
abandon the
judgment because it's non-binding judgment with two. ושניים שעשו פשרה אין בעלי
דינים יכולים לחזור בהן. ushnayim she'asu psharah ein ba'alei dinim yecholim lachzor
bahen. If two were in judgment then you could abandon the judgment
because it's non-binding judgment with two. But פשרה psharah with two, if
that's who you accepted to rule for you and to rule binding
arbitration, it is binding. So anyway you see here that two is
not binding as דין, din, and that's against Shmuel. Shmuel says two
is binding as דין. din. So וכי תימא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי
שמעון גמליאל. vechi teima pligi rabbanan aleih deRabbi Shimon Gamliel. Now maybe
the Rabbis argue with Rabbi Shimon Gamliel. Maybe what Shmuel would say
is that there's a, you know, Shimon Gamliel is not the way
we פסקן, pasken, there's an opinion that disagrees and that says two
is binding.
ואמר רבי אבהו, ve'amar Rabbi Abbahu, but one minute, Rabbi Abbahu says
ששניים שדנו לדברי הכל אין דיניהם דין. sheshnayim shedannu ledivrei hakol ein
dineihem din. He backs up Rabbi Shimon Gamliel and he says Rabbi
Shimon Gamliel's position is universal, that two people, everybody agrees, is not
a good בית דין. beit din. So how could Shmuel say a
בית דין beit din of two is binding? So the גמרא Gemorah
says גברא אגברא קרמית, gavra agavra karemita, what? So you're going to
throw one Rabbi against another Rabbi? Rabbi Abbahu thinks that this is
a universal פסק psak that two people isn't a good בית דין,
beit din, and Shmuel disagrees. Shmuel thinks two people is a good
בית דין. beit din. Okay, so now we've got, of course, three
is your standard בית דין, beit din, two people is a debate
here, Shmuel says it's good but it's בית דין חצוף, beit din
chatzuf, others say it's no good. And then we had the earlier
גמרא Gemorah that spoke about יחיד מומחה. yachid mumche. Okay, and there
it seems like everybody said יחיד מומחה yachid mumche was good. So,
you know, what's that about? So again תוספות Tosafot says that was
a special תקנת דרבנן takanat deRabbanan to allow for more דיני ממונות
dinei mamonot access and that's why maybe that גמרא Gemorah specifically emphasized
the idea of מומחה. mumche. These discussions of three and two are
not discussing מומחה. mumche. That required מומחה mumche and maybe the מומחה
mumche with the licensing and מומחה לרבים mumche lerabbim and everybody knows
you're an expert and all of that, that was a case where
we allowed even one person to judge. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemorah says like this. גופא. gufa. Now, אמר רבי אבהו שניים שדנו
דיני ממונות לדברי הכל אין דיניהם דין. amar Rabbi Abbahu shnayim shedannu
dinei mamonot ledivrei hakol ein dineihem din. איתיביה, eitiveih, I'll ask you
on this that you say that less than two isn't binding at
all. איתיבי רב אבא לרבי אבהו, eitivei Rav Abba leRabbi Abbahu, or
two isn't binding and certainly less than two isn't binding. So דן
את הדין, dan et hadin, this is what we also saw this
in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, וזיכה את החייב וחיייב את הזכאי טימא את
הטהור וטיהר את הטמא, vezika et hachayav vechiyav et hazakai tima et
hatahor vetiher et hatamei, so somebody gave a wrong ruling, and notice
it's all in the singular, מה שעשה עשוי ומשלם מביתו, ma she'asa
asui umeshalem mibeito, it's binding and now you have to pay up.
And now why? So look, how can it be one person is
judging? Now you might be inclined to say, well maybe this was
the case of יחיד מומחה. yachid mumche. But if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, look at the רש"י Rashi second two
lines from the top, דן את הדין במומחה ליכא למימר, dan et
hadin bemumche leika lemeimar, you can't say oh this is different it's
יחיד מומחה, yachid mumche, מדיקתני סיפא אם היה מומחה לבית דין, mideikatani
seifa im haya mumche lebeit din, because the end of this teaching
is that if the guy was a מומחה mumche he doesn't have
to pay even if he פסקן paskened incorrectly. So the whole point
of this משנה mishna is that you're liable if you're not a
מומחה. mumche. If you're a מומחה mumche you're not liable. So here
you have a case by a יחיד yachid who's not a מומחה
mumche and the judgment is binding. How does that fit with everything
we've been saying? We've allowed a יחיד מומחה, yachid mumche, two is
debated, but a יחיד yachid who's not a מומחה mumche is certainly
not binding, so what's going on here? So it says הכא במאי
עסקינן דקיבלו עלייהו, hacha bemai askinan dekiblu aleihu, this you should hear
the echoes of the ירושלמי Yerushalmi here. You're right, one person who's
not a מומחה mumche can't judge, meaning they can't compel other people
to come to them, right? And the same and the debate was,
can two? But, you know, but if קיבלו עלייהו kiblu aleihu that
works. Okay, so the גמרא Gemorah says אי הכי, ei hachi, if
that's true, אמאי משלם מביתו, amai meshalem mibeito, like we saw in
the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, if they've accepted his judgment then whatever he says
should be binding, how could there ever be a mistake? Right? Maybe
it's more like binding arbitration. Right? That's what the גמרא Gemorah assumes
when קיבלו עלייהו kiblu aleihu sort of puts you in, should that
put you in a binding arbitration and then you can't really be
finding a mistake? So the גמרא Gemorah says no, דאמרו ליה דיינת
לן דין תורה, de'amru leih dayant lan din Torah, right? This is,
hopefully you remember this from the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Yes they accepted his
authority but at the end of the day they didn't want him
to judge based on his שיקול הדעת. shikul hadaat. Don't judge based
on your own like binding arbitration. We demand that the outcome be
דין תורה. din Torah. So on the one hand because it's קיבלו
עלייהו kiblu aleihu it allows him to judge even though he's an
individual and on the other hand because they're demanding דין תורה din
Torah they could say that the judgment was in error. It's not
just binding arbitration whatever you say. It's binding only to the degree
that we can say that it's objectively consistent with הלכה halacha and
that therefore allows The balance
of משלם מביתו. meshallem mibeiso. Okay? So by the way, just because
it's getting I think a little confusing, okay? You have, I know
you, but you have יחיד מומחה, yachid mumche, okay? And there that
question was גמיר וסביר וסביר, gamir vesavir vesavir, and the question was
do you also need it to be נוטל רשות. notel reshus. נוטל
רשות notel reshus is definitely work to say פטור מלשלם, patur milishallem,
okay? And that type of a case, that's one case, and that
works, okay? And that presumably is that you can compel judgment in
that case. It's even לא קיבלו עליי. lo kiblu alai. You have
שנים שדנו, shenayim shedanu, right? where שמואל Shmuel says it's good, but
it's חצוף, chatzuf,
right? and רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu and others say no good. And
then of course you've got three, which is of course that's your
standard בית דין. beis din. So these, these are cases where we're
talking about like compelling, okay? Can you basically go ahead and force
people, it doesn't require whether קיבלו עלייהו. kiblu alayhu. I can force
you to come in front of one of these courts, okay?
Can one of those litigants force the other?
Yeah, I mean there's always a question of jurisdiction. No, let's say
a litigant, there's always a question of jurisdiction, okay?
But assuming that there is jurisdiction, one can force the other, okay?
And this type of a case, it's also פטור מלשלם, patur milishallem,
right? because that's what רש״י Rashi said at the end of that
משנה, mishna, דנה את הדין זיכה את החייב. dana es hadin zikkah
es hachayav. It says if you were a מומחה, mumche, you're פטור
מלשלם. patur milishallem. Didn't תוספות Tosafos go? Right. So as opposed to
when you hear just a יחיד אינו מומחה,
yachid eino
mumche, okay? That only works if קיבל עלייהו kibel alayhu
and in that case you're חייב לשלם. chayav lishallem. But the question
is why are you חייב לשלם chayav lishallem if it's קיבל עלייהו,
kibel alayhu, shouldn't that just make it binding arbitration? So it says
קיבל עלייהו kibel alayhu but he says דין תורה, din torah, okay?
and therefore you could be חייב לשלם chayav lishallem because yes we
accepted your authority, okay? but you have to come out with an
objectively true thing and that's contrasted to of course what could be
like ביצוע bitzua or פשרה peshara or something like that which would
be קיבל עלייהו, kibel alayhu, קיבלו עלייהו kiblu alayhu
without דין תורה, din torah, which means whatever you say is going
to be binding.
Yes, didn't תוספות Tosafos on עמוד א׳ amud aleph say קמשי דרבי
אבהו דלא קיבלוה עלייהו כלל. kamshei d'Rabbi Abahu d'lo kibluha alayhu klal.
What's how do you? What? On עמוד א׳ amud aleph תוספות Tosafos
דבור המתחיל דלא קיבלוה
עלייהו כלל.
dibbur hamaschil d'lo kibluha
alayhu klal.
Where are you?
עמוד א׳ amud aleph תוספות Tosafos אינו זיל. eino zil.
I have to look at it. Okay, let's go on. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. Okay, so it says שקיבלו
עלייהו יחיד בדין תורה. she-kiblu alayhu yachid b'din torah. Okay, אמר רב
ספרא לרבי אבא. amar Rav Sappa l'Rabbi Abba. So רב ספרא Rav
Sappa said to רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, דטעה במאי? d'tah b'mai? what
was the mistake? אילימא דטעה בדבר משנה, ileima d'tah b'dvar mishna,
it was a mistake in דבר משנה, dvar mishna, which means like
black letter law, okay? something that was explicit.
So therefore ואמר רבי ששת אמר רבי אמי ורבי אסי טעה בדבר
משנה חוזר, v'amar Rabbi Sheshes amar Rabbi Ami v'Rabbi Assi tah b'dvar
mishna chozer, that if it was you clearly made a mistake in
דבר משנה, dvar mishna, it's not that it's binding and you have
to pay, then it wasn't even a good judgment and therefore you
won't pay because we reverse the whole ruling. Now Erika asked the
other day, who gets to decide that it was a mistake? That's
not decided. Do I myself the דיין dayan realize, oh my god,
I just realized I made a huge mistake? Right, there's no like
appeals system. Okay, I mean, you know, we could discuss that if
there was a בית דין beis din of כ״ג, chaf-gimmel, but, you
know, maybe that creates like an appeals type of a system, even
there it's only because if we don't know we decide to go
to that בית דין, beis din, we sort of like self-refer it.
Okay, this sounds more like I myself acknowledge that it was a
mistake or maybe all the other rabbis in the town all got
up and said that I made it's not exactly clear who identifies
that it's a טועה. to'eh.
But if it doesn't mean that like if then you said okay
you have to pay so and so.
I say Michael pay David, you pay David a thousand dollars, and
then I realize or somebody brought to my attention or everybody came
and screamed that I violated an explicit, you know, black letter law,
then I don't have to reimburse Michael, I say David's gotta give
the money back to Michael. Okay. So טעה בדבר משנה חוזר, tah
b'dvar mishna chozer, אלא דטעה בשיקול הדעת. ela d'tah b'shikul hadaas. It
was a judgment call. So what's a judgment call that's still a
mistake? If it's a judgment call how is it a mistake?
Okay. היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case בשיקול הדעת? b'shikul hadaas?
אמר רב פפא כגון תרי תנאי ותרי אמוראי דפליגי אהדדי. amar Rav
Papa kegon t'rei tanna'ei v'trei amora'ei d'paligi adadi. Let's say it's a
debate and it's a debate of two תנאים tannaim or two אמוראים
amoraim and they're equally weighted. Okay. So it's not like you have
a million rabbis say one thing and one rabbi says another. It's
an equally weighted debate. So it's a judgment call. ולא איתמר הלכתא
לא כמר ולא כמר v'lo ismar hilchesa lo k'mar v'lo k'mar and
there's been no consensus how we rule. So okay, that all sounds
terrific, so then where's the mistake? It sounds like you're free to
use your judgment. No. וסוגיא דעלמא אליבא דחד מנייהו. v'sugya d'alma aliba
d'chad mineihu. But
the
So the הילוך hiluch Rashi says הילוך דינא. hiluch dina. The general
practice among judges. It’s not officially there’s a ruling, this is the
ruling, but the general practice among judges is in a certain way.
וזל ועבד כאידך Vezal veavad keidach and he went ahead and he
ruled like the other one. היינו שיקול הדעת. Haynu shikul hadaas. That’s
a judgment call. Now I would like to know why is it
a mistake? It might be that there’s a general practice among judges
to go one way, but I personally think it’s wrong, I personally
think the other way. Where’s the טעות? to'us? That’s what is still
not clear. Is the טעות to'us because maybe I didn’t realize that
there was an established sort of consensus and practice?
Had I known that the standard practice among judges was a certain
way, I would have gone that way, but I didn’t realize it.
Maybe that’s the case. But if I did realize it, aren’t I
allowed to go by a minority’s opinion before there’s been an absolute
פסק? psak? So it’s not exactly clear where here is the טעות.
to'us. But the גמרא Gemara says because obviously the ruling is legitimate,
it’s not going to be חוזר. chozer. It’s not like it was
clearly wrong. It went against the consensus maybe, but it’s not clearly
wrong, so it’s not חוזר. chozer. But because it’s wrong enough, you
have to pay back the other guy. But I have to tell
you I am still conflicted about understanding exactly what makes it wrong
at all. And the best I can say is I would have
to admit that had I known that this was the general practice
in the legal community, I wouldn’t have necessarily done that. I do
need to stop here and say that this גמרא Gemara and the
discussion in the ראשונים rishonim around this גמרא Gemara becomes critically important
for questions of canonization and
sources of legal הלכה halacha authority. Because for example, there is a
discussion in the ראשונים rishonim which is if somebody goes ahead and
rules in a position against the גאונים, geonim, against a consensus of
the גאונים, geonim, is that טועה בדבר משנה? to'eh bidvar mishna? And
that's a whole question about what is the authority of the גאונים.
geonim. Can I as a ראשון, rishon, if I was רמב"ם Rambam
or רמב"ן Ramban or whatever, can I go ahead and say I
don't care what the גאונים geonim say, here's how I'm saying it?
Or no, that's טועה בדבר משנה. to'eh bidvar mishna. So ultimately that's
a question of what is the binding authority of the גאונים? geonim?
Let’s say I rule like a ירושלמי Yerushalmi against a בבלי. Bavli.
Let’s say I go ahead and I rule against the שולחן ערוך.
Shulchan Aruch. Am I טועה בדבר משנה? to'eh bidvar mishna? So the
question of what is דבר משנה, dvar mishna, what is black-letter law,
what type of work or authority has you can't go against, is
ultimately the question of what has been canonized as our הלכתי halachic
works. So even though obviously the גמרא Gemara isn't giving an answer
to that, by framing this category, this becomes the framework in which
פוסקים poskim discuss what are the types of canonical authorities within
הלכה. halacha.
Okay.
Let's just read a little bit more to the bottom here and
then we'll get to the more פשרה pishara things tomorrow, just give
me two more minutes. So the גמרא Gemara says לימא כתנאי. Leima
ketannai. Let's say this question about whether you need two or whether
two can work as a בית דין beis din or not is
tied to a debate of תנאים. tannaim. ביצוע בשלושה דברי רבי מאיר,
Bitzoa bishlosha divrei Rabbi Meir, because Rabbi Meir says compromises with three.
וחכמים אומרים פשרה ביחיד. Vachachamim omrim pshara beyachid. Notice the switch from
ביצוע bitzoa to פשרה. pishara. Some have the גרסא girsa ביצוע. bitzoa.
But clearly these were words that were used somewhat interchangeably at different
times. Anyway, they say no, no, no, ביצוע bitzoa can even be
done, binding arbitration can even be done with one. So what’s this
debate of three and one? סברוהו, Savruha, we’re assuming, דכולי עלמא מקישין
פשרה לדין, dechei alma makishin pshara ledin, that binding arbitration has the
same requirements in terms of the compromise of the court, the composition
of the court as דין din does. מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? Mai
lav beha kamiflegi? So this must be the debate. דמר סבר דין
בשלושה Demar savar din bishlosha ומר סבר דין בשניים. umar savar din
bishnayim. The one that says that binding arbitration is three says דין
din is three, and the one that says binding arbitration is two
is one says that דין din is two. So we really should
say דין din is one, which really reflects the idea that the
one who says two might really be also be saying in the
end of the day one. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says לא. Lo.
No, not necessarily. דכולי עלמא דין בשלושה. Dechei alma din bishlosha. Everybody
could agree that when it comes to דין, din, that’s your classic
court of three. והכא בהא קמיפלגי. Vehacha beha kamiflegi. Here’s the debate.
דמר סבר מקישין פשרה לדין, Demar savar makishin pshara ledin, that binding
arbitration has to function like דין din and requires a בית דין
beis din of three. ומר סבר לא מקישין פשרה לדין Umar savar
lo makishin pshara ledin if it does not. So this question, does
binding arbitration need a three, is similar to the issues we were
discussing of how much is פשרה pishara have elements of דין, din,
have elements of we're going to be also assessing who's right and
who's wrong, we're not just going to be coming up with a.
compromise. It certainly suggests that type of an idea. So this could
be a debate about the nature of פשרה *peshara* and not a
debate about דין *din*. דין *din* we could all agree is three.
Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says לימא תלתא תנאי בפשרה *Leima tlata
tanna'ei bi-peshara*. Let's say there's three opinions when it comes to this
idea of פשרה *peshara*. דמר סבר בשלושה ומר סבר בשנים ומר סבר
ביחיד *De-mar savar bi-shelosha u-mar savar bi-shenayim u-mar savar be-yachid*. We've got
three opinions here. That we've got the idea of three, that was
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. We've got the idea of one, that was
the idea here of the חכמים *Chachamim*. And we have the idea
of two, because if you remember before, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel* said compared three versus two of פשרה *peshara* versus
דין *din*. So it seems like we have three possibilities of פשרה
*peshara*: one, two, and three, right? So that's pretty much it sounds
that way. So אמר רבי אחא בריה דרב איקא ואי תימא רב
יימר בר שלמיא *Amar Rabbi Acha bereih de-Rav Ika ve-i teima Rav
Yeimar bar Shelamya*, מאן דאמר תרי אפילו חד נמי *man de-amar terei
afilu chad nami*. No, no, no. When you say פשרה *peshara* is
with two, you really concede that פשרה *peshara* could be done by
one. So why were you saying two? דהאי דקאמר תרי כדי להוי
ליה סהדי *De-hai de-ka-amar terei kedei le-hava lei sahedi*. Because you're going
to want witnesses to, you know, I said I ruled this way,
this was the binding arbitration, and you're going to walk out of
the case and each one of you's going to claim I said
something else. Okay, so therefore, if we say two, we're really not
saying that you need two to make it binding, but we're going
to talk about doing פשרה *peshara* with two because that's just a
smart procedure. I'm going to want to have somebody else on the
court so we can then both testify that this was our final
decision. Okay, so what we have is that דין *din* is obviously
classic דין *din* is three. There are debates about two and one,
etc. יחיד מומחה *yachid mumche* or two is debated. יחיד מומחה *yachid
mumche* seems to be agreed. And then when it comes to פשרה
*peshara* over here, we have the possibilities of three and one, the
גמרא *Gemara* sort of bracketing the idea of two. Okay, but there's
an opinion that even פשרה *peshara*, which is not this middle case
of קיבלו עלייהו בדין תורה *kiblu aleihu be-din torah*, but actual פשרה
בביצוע *peshara be-vitzua*, that it's saying it sounds like three ideas, but
we'll say two: three, which makes it very much like דין *din*
and demands three, or one, which makes it something that is different
from דין *din*. Obviously, it's not יחיד מומחה *yachid mumche*. Okay, so
let's stop here and we will pick up with this tomorrow.